[
  {
    "question": "Which orientation of a pressure-measuring inlet with respect to the flow direction corresponds to which type of pressure being measured and why?",
    "answer": "If the fluid flows perpendicular to the inlet and it is facing the flow, stagnation pressure is measured because the fluid's velocity is brought to zero. If the fluid flows parallel to the inlet, static pressure is measured because the fluid is in motion, and according to Bernoulli's Principle, the static pressure of a fluid decreases along a streamline as its velocity increases.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "When does a heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs achieve its highest possible efficiency?",
    "answer": "A heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs with temperatures T1 and T2 achieves its highest possible efficiency (n) when the ratio of T1 to T2 equals the ratio of heat transfer (Q1) from T1 to heat transfer (Q2) to T2. In this case, T1 is the warmer reservoir and T2 is the cooler reservoir, and the system is reversible.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "Why don't the values of stagnation properties change during an isentropic process?",
    "answer": "During an isentropic process, there is no energy loss, as it is also adiabatic and reversible. This means that static and dynamic properties can change, but overall stagnation properties will remain unchanged during an isentropic process.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "When can Bernoulli's Principle be applied and why?",
    "answer": "Bernoulli's Principle can only be applied along a streamline in steady, inviscid, and incompressible flow. It can be applied across streamlines only when they are parallel to each other and the flow is still steady, inviscid, and incompressible. This is because Bernoulli's Principle is a relationship between static pressure and velocity, which assumes constant density and no energy losses.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of flow experiencing an adverse pressure gradient?",
    "answer": "In viscous flow experiencing an adverse pressure gradient, the force originating from pressure differences in a pipe or other fluid vessel is directing the fluid in the opposite direction from which one of the surfaces of the vessel is moving. This causes the fluid and streamlines close to the moving surface to flow in the same direction that this surface is moving due to friction. As this momentum diffuses outward, the force generated from the pressure difference in the pipe becomes the driving force of the fluid, causing the flow to shift in this direction. This is an example of both Couette Flow and Poiseuille Flow occurring in opposite directions.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens as you increase the pressure difference between the entrance and exit of a converging-diverging nozzle?",
    "answer": "This is done by decreasing the static pressure at the exit. If the flow entering the nozzle is subsonic, it will be choked at the throat if the ratio of exit static pressure to inlet stagnation pressure is 0.5283 or below. As you decrease this ratio, the location of the normal shock in the diverging section moves farther and farther down the nozzle towards the exit until it reaches the exit. This is assuming the flow is inviscid, and does not affect the flow conditions before the throat.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main characteristics of an expansion fan and why are these characteristics observed?",
    "answer": "An expansion fan consists of supersonic flow reaching a sharp convex corner where a series of Mach waves form a so-called fan. After the expansion fan, the Mach number increases, the static pressure, temperature, density, and enthalpy decrease, and the stagnation properties remain the same. The Mach number increases because the area of the flow increases, which is commonly observed for supersonic flow. The stagnation properties remain the same because the flow is isentropic, which stems from the fact that the changes across each individual Mach wave are minuscule. The overall flow property changes across an expansion fan are opposite from the overall flow property changes across normal and oblique shocks.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prandtl%E2%80%93Meyer_expansion_fan"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the wedge angle (theta) causing an oblique shock affect?",
    "answer": "For a given Mach number, there exists a maximum wedge angle (max theta) beyond which the oblique shock becomes a detached bow shock that occurs before the wedge. For a wedge angle below this maximum wedge angle, there are two possible types of shocks: strong shocks and weak shocks. Strong shocks have a higher wave angle than weak shocks and strong shocks reduce the Mach number by more. Weak shocks are more common than strong shocks and are almost always chosen over strong shocks in AE 2010.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the use of the polytropic process equation?",
    "answer": "The polytropic index (n) of the equation explains what type of process is occurring during compression or expansion. When n equals gamma, the process is isentropic. When n equals 1, the process is isothermal. When n equals 0, the process is isobaric. When n equals infinity, the process is isochoric. When n is in between 1 and gamma, the process is non-adiabatic and there is some heat transfer.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "A fluid with a density of 1.125 kg/m^3 travels at 10 m/s through a main, cylindrical pipe with a diameter of 0.25 m that splits into two smaller pipes with a diameter of 0.1 m. The pressure at the end of these smaller pipes is the ambient pressure, 101325 Pa. The pressure upstream of the split is 3 bar and the velocity of the fluid exiting the pipes is 50 m/s. What is the force that the walls of the pipe exert on the fluid?",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  rho = 1.125 # Density (kg/m^3)\n  p1 = 300000 # Inlet Pressure (Pa)\n  p2 = 101325 # Outlet Pressure (Pa)\n  A1 = (3.1415/4)*(0.25**2) # Inlet Area (m^2)\n  A2 = (3.1415/4)*(0.1**2) # Outlet Area (m^2)\n  v1 = 10 Inlet velocity (m/s)\n  v2 = 50 Outlet velocity (m/s)\n\n  # Apply Steady Flow Momentum Equation\n  F = (p1*A1) - (p2*A2) - (p2*A2) + (rho*(v2**2)*A2) - (rho*(v1**2)*A1)\n\n  print('Force exerted on the fluid:', F, 'N')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code utilizes the Steady Flow Momentum Equation, which is a statement on Newton's 2nd Law, F=ma. It ",
      "reference": "https://www.homepages.ucl.ac.uk/~uceseug/Fluids2/Problems_2_Slides.pdf"

  },
  {
    "question": "A diverging nozzle with circular cross-sectional area contains water (density equals 1000 kg/m^3) flowing at a speed of 5 m/s at the inlet. The radius at the exit is 3 times the radius at the inlet. What is the velocity of the water at the outlet?",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  rho = 1000 # Density (kg/m^3)\n  r1overr2 = 1/3 # Ratio of exit radius to inlet radius\n  v1 = 5 # Inlet Velocity (m/s)\n  pi = 3.1415 # pi\n\n  # Apply continuity equation\n  v2 = (rho * v1 * pi * (r1overr2)**2)/(rho * pi)\n\n  print('The water's exit velocity:', v2, 'm/s')\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code utilizes the continuity equation that states that mass must be conserved when entering or exiting a control volume. This is expressed as mass flow rates at the inlet and exit equaling each other.",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "A perfect gas is compressed in a thermally insulated piston adiabatically and reversibly to a temperature of 500 K. Its molar mass is 28.02 g/mol and has a constant pressure specific heat capacity (cp) of 1039 J/(kg*K). Its initial pressure and temperature is 50000 Pa and 280 K. What is the final pressure of the gas?",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  T1 = 280 # initial temperature (K)\n  T2 = 500 # final temperature (K)\n  p1 = 50000 # initial pressure (Pa)\n  cp = 1039 # constant pressure heat capacity (J/(kg*K))\n  M = 0.02802 # molar mass of unknown gas (kg/mol)\n  Rbar = 8.3145 # universal gas constant (J/(mol*K))\n\n  # Find the specific gas constant (R)\n  R = Rbar/M\n\n  # Find the gas's value of gamma (y)\n  y = cp/(cp-R)\n\n  # Apply isentropic gas relation\n  p2 = p1 * ((T2/T1)**(y/(y-1)))\n\n  print('Final pressure of the gas:', p2, 'Pa')\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code uses three equations: the specific gas equation, an equation for gamma, and an isentropic gas relation between pressure and temperature. First, the molar mass of the gas is used to find the specific gas constant which is then used to find gamma by substituing (cp-R) for cv (cv is the constant volume specific heat capacity). Since the process is adiabatic and reversible, it must be isentropic, so the isentropic gas relationship is then applied to find p2.",
    "reference": "https://learncheme.com/quiz-yourself/interactive-self-study-modules/adiabatic-reversible-expansion-and-compression/adiabatic-reversible-expansion-and-compression-example-problems/"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air initially at 50 degrees Celsius flows over a wedge at a speed of 700 m/s. An oblique shock is formed at the start of this wedge, and the wave angle (beta) is measured to be 40 degrees. What is the wedge angle (theta)? Assume a gamma (y) value of 1.4 and an R value of 287.",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  T1 = 50 # initial temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  v1 = 700 # initial velocity (m/s)\n  B = np.deg2rad(40) # wave angle (radians)\n  y = 1.4 # gamma value\n  R = 287 # gas constant for air (J/(kg*K))\n\n  # Find the speed of sound before the shock to find the Mach number\n  a = np.sqrt(y * R * (T1 + 273.15))\n  M1 = v1/a\n\n  # Find the wedge angle (theta)\n  theta = np.arctan((2/np.tan(B)) * ((((M1**2)*(np.sin(B))**2)-1)/(((M1**2)*(y+np.cos(2*B)))+2)))\n  theta = np.rad2deg(theta)\n\n  print('Wedge angle:', theta, 'degrees')\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code utilizes the equation for wedge angle, which is used to find the wedge angle for various Mach numbers in the oblique shock tables. First, the Mach number needs to be found by finding the speed of sound using the equation a = sqrt(y*R*T1). Then, the values are plugged into the equation. This means that this problem can also be solved using the oblique shock tables instead of using this equation. This problem assumes the oblique shock is weak and that the gas is perfect.",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "A perfect gas flows steadily through a vertically oriented turbine which triples the velocity of the air from the inlet to the outlet. Its inlet is located 30 meters above its outlet and its constant pressure specific heat capacity (cp) is 910 J/(kg*K). The temperature of the gas at the inlet is 25 degrees Celsius and at the outlet its temperature is 97 degrees Celsius. Calculate the specific work done on the gas if the velocity at the inlet is 100 m/s and there is no heat loss. Account for changes in potential and kinetic energy.",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  cp = 910 # constant pressure specific heat capacity (J/(kg*K))\n  T1 = 25 # initial temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  T2 = 97 # final temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  dz = -30 # change in height (m)\n  v1 = 100 # initial velocity (m/s)\n  v2overv1 = 3 # ratio of final velocity to initial velocity\n  g = 9.81 # gravitational constant (m/s^2)\n\n  # Convert temperatures to Kelvin\n  T1 = T1 + 273.25\n  T2 = T2 + 273.15\n\n  # Express change in specific enthalpy in cv times dT\n  dh = cp * (T2-T1)\n\n  # Apply steady flow energy equation after dividing through by m dot\n  w = dh + 0.5*(((v2overv1*v1)**2) - v1**2) + g*dz\n\n  print('Specific work done on the gas:', w, 'J/kg')\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code utilizes the steady flow energy equation and some assumptions to make it more practical. Since the gas is perfect, the change in enthalpy can be expressed as cp times the change in temperature, and the statement of no heat loss means that the process can be considered adiabatic. This problem takes into account the changes in velocity and height, which affect the kinetic and potential energies of the system. Many problems only account for the change in internal energy, but with large changes in velocity and height, it is necessary to include these other forms of energy in the equation.",
    "reference": "https://www.studocu.com/en-gb/document/imperial-college-london/engineering-materials/steady-flow-energy-problems/14305523 (Example 2)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A gas flows through a converging-diverging nozzle and the flow is choked at the throat. The static pressure before the shock is 0.5 bar and the static pressure after the shock is 3 bar. Using the normal shock relations, find the ratio of density after the shock to density before the shock. Assume a gamma (y) value of 1.333",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  p1 = 50000 # static pressure before shock (Pa)\n  p2 = 300000 # static pressure after shock (Pa)\n  y = 1.333 # gamma value\n\n  # Find Mach number before shock\n  M = np.sqrt(((p2/p1)+((y-1)/(y+1))) * ((y+1)/(2*y)))\n\n  # Find density ratio\n  rho2overrho1 = ((2/(y+1)) * (1/(M**2))) + ((y-1)/(y+1))\n\n  print('Ratio of density after the shock to density before the shock:', rho2overrho1)\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code utilizes the normal shock relations for static pressure before and after a shock and density before and after a shock. First, the static pressure ratio is used to find the Mach number before the shock, and then this is used to find the density ratio. This process can also be done using the normal shock tables. This question assumes there is no friction.",
    "reference":""
  },
  {
    "question": "A perfect gas flows through a pipe that has a section that adds heat from an external source. Assume gamma (y) is 1.4 and the specific gas constant is 300 J/(kg*K). This causes both the temperature and pressure of the gas to triple. In another section of the pipe, there is a high amount of friction resulting in irreversible specific entropy increase of 40 J/(kg*K). Find the net increase in specific entropy throughout these sections.",
    "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  y = 1.4 # gamma value\n  R = 300 # specific gas constant (J/(kg*K))\n  T2overT1 = 3 # ratio of T2 to T1\n  p2overp1 = 3 # ratio of p2 to p1\n  ds_irrev = 40 # increase in specific entropy from the irreversible friction (J/(kg*K))\n\n  # Find cp from gamma (y) and R\n  cp = (y*R)/(y-1)\n\n  # Find change in specific entropy from external heat source\n  ds_rev = (cp*np.log(T2overT1)) - (R*np.log(p2overp1))\n\n  # Find the net change in specific entropy\n  ds_net = ds_irrev + ds_rev\n\n  print('Net increase in specific entropy:', ds_net, 'J/(kg*K)')\n      ",
    "explanation": "This code utilizes an equation derived from the specific Tds equations. This code first finds cp from gamma (y) and the specific gas constant to find the change in specific entropy for the reversible addition of heat from an external source. There is also a source of entropy from the irreversible process of frictional losses that is added to the first specific entropy change to get the net change in entropy for this process of a perfect gas flowing through a pipe. This assumes that there isn't friction in the part of the pipe with the external heat source.",
    "reference":""
  }
]